[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you please visit se
radio.net survey to share a little
information about your professional
interests and listening habits
it takes less than two minutes to help
us continue to make se radio even better
the responses to the survey are
completely confidential
that's s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host jeff
doolittle i'm excited to invite l peter
deutsch
as our guest on the show today el peter
deutsch is best known as the original
and primary author of ghost script the
inventor of the term
just in time compilation in connection
with his early jit compiler for small
talk 80
and one of several independent
originators of simultaneous libre and
commercial software licensing
he has also contributed through
documentation as writer of the rfcs for
deflate
zip and gzip and through conference
presentations on a variety of topics
including software patents and software
security
peter welcome to software engineering
radio thank you i'm delighted to be here
today
so you mentioned in a previous
conversation we had that
you've been in the industry for about 60
years
and i imagine you've seen a lot in those
60 years and there's probably not a lot
of people who can claim that they've had
a 60-year career
in the software industry at this point
that's probably right
it wasn't very customary for someone to
start writing software at the age of 14
when i started
these days you know people start coding
in grade school
right some do that's yeah it's true in
fact my first
programming class was in junior high
school on a commodore 64 back in the 80s
so yeah definitely started i guess we're
at the same age as you i suppose but
maybe a little younger
well we're here to talk about today is
something that a lot of people have
probably heard of
and how much they thought about them and
where they came from and how they are
relevant
is a great conversation for us to have
so
i'm referring to of course the fallacies
of distributed computing
and in the show notes we'll put a link
into the wikipedia article on those
which as we might explore during this
show may not be entirely accurate and
hopefully as a result of this show we
can help correct some of the
mistakes or errors that might exist in
that article
but let's start with what's the
background of these fallacies peter
how did they come about and sort of what
time frame did these fallacies come into
existence
so my contribution to the fallacies came
about
during a year and a half that i was
working at the
what was in sun microsystems which was
from the latter part of 1991 to the
earlier part of 1993
so at least to that extent the dates in
the wikipedia article are incorrect
i'm not a networking guy i've done very
very little with networking technology
but i think as part of the kind of new
hire hazing process at sun
the first thing that they had me do was
co-chair
a working group on mobile computing
strategy
and my co-chair was a talented engineer
named carolyn terby phil
and i believe she had primarily a
hardware background
so the two of us you know set out to
talk to the engineers within sun to find
out what sun was doing and
you know get some ideas as to what sun
might do in the future
and it was in in the course of those
investigations and learning
about sun's work and networking that i
came up with my contribution to the list
of fallacies when i arrived at sun the
first four fallacies
were already known and established and i
knew that they'd been originated by one
of the two lion brothers and i didn't
remember whether it was tom or dick
and then i added the
next four and i gave a presentation at
sun
during my time there that if i remember
correctly had all eight of them in it
so in the course of that investigation
at sun
something became pretty clear to me
which was that at the time
sun had a couple things going for it but
the most
important one was that they understood
networking you know protocols and
network architecture in a way that
their competitors did not
and so but they were developing
had developed i guess this kind of
clunky bulky
mobile device which today i guess we
would call a laptop
and it seemed that they wanted some
guidance
on how to proceed in that arena
well we wrote a report and what we said
i wrote most of the report reporters i
recall and what
the report said was look sun does not
have
a good competitive differentiator in the
hardware arena
the japanese and korean companies are
better set up
to move forward they were already ahead
of sun at that point if i remember right
but the thing that sun does have as a
differentiator
is engineering depth in networking and
network protocols
so sun's strategic path forward
in network to be successful in the
mobile space
is to develop and offer
the non-mobile infrastructure for mobile
devices
and we didn't have the terminology for
it then but in retrospect
what i was basically recommending was
that sun
be a groundbreaker in what today is
called cloud computing
or server-based computing well this was
you know the early 1990s and when i've
been told by someone
who was in a position to know that when
this
report got to the desk of scott mcneely
who was the
ceo of sun at the time that he read the
report
said who are these bozos and tossed it
in the trash
and having been in retrospect
right brings me a certain amount of
satisfaction and it does of course make
me wonder and possibly our listeners as
well how the world might have been
different if the reaction had been
different at that time and
i even imagined that many of our
listeners don't even know what sun
microsystems
is or was that's right they
made some other i think perhaps not
great strategic choices and wound up
being
gobbled up and then pretty much
dismembered by oracle
right and of course ideas are a dime a
dozen and what matters is execution so
even if the ideas had been embraced it
didn't guarantee success but
it is interesting to think about the the
possibility that we could have had
things differently you know the 90s
really from my recollection were more of
the client server era in many ways but
it sounds like
the report was in a way leap frogging
that and saying hey let's get past that
and let's actually embrace
what you know what i think we now call
network computing or as you said the
cloud
so you know i don't remember exactly
what we said and of course i i didn't
take away
any copies of it but i'd like to think
that we were maybe a little bit ahead of
the time
you know you talk about good ideas not
always coming to fruition
the one that in the networking arena
that i think of right away
is xerox and xns
you know ipv4 was an outgrowth
of what was basically the successor
to the original arpanet design and ipv4
is
it's a great architecture and it's
served very well
but you know it it's run into
limitations it's run into a capacity
limitation which nobody i think ever
would have foreseen
and there are differences of opinion
about how good ipv6 is i'm not qualified
to weigh in on that
but the thing that i did want to you
know want to mention is that xerox
actually developed their own
competitor if you will to ip it was
called xns
and it greatly predated ipv6
and it was based on a
very different principle from ipv4
with ipv4 one of the
problems and one of the things that has
you know made
approaching the capacity of the ip
address space difficult
is that ip addresses combine
identification with routing
if you look at the way an ipv4 address
is put together
part of the address basically says or
at least started out saying something
about what network
that device was attached to and if
networks grow at different rates and you
know if different geographic areas
you know have different needs in terms
of their
amount of name space the ipv4 model
just isn't cut out for it that's a
fascinating insight right that the
topology was coupled to the routing
absolutely i mean or vice versa vice
versa yeah i'm not
the first and i'm sure i'm not the
thousandth person who's made the
observation that this had a
bad effect on on the evolution of the
network but but
it's something that that people come to
realize the interesting thing about xns
is that as i said it far predates ipv6
and it
decoupled routing from naming completely
devices had permanent
if i recall correctly 48-bit names what
do they
we know as mac addresses they did not
have ip addresses in the sense
of ipv4 and furthermore
those unique ids were not
necessarily arranged or partitioned in
any way that had anything to do with
geography
that architecture puts a much greater
load
on routers because they now have to keep
routing information for every device
a full xns address consisted of a 48-bit
device id and a 32-bit
again unstructured unique id for a
network
so the idea was that routers would
expect people to be supplying
these whatever it would be 80-bit
addresses and would start out by routing
packets to
the network specified by the 32-bit
address
which might be wrong it was only
supposed to be a hint a very reliable
hint
but if a device moved from one network
to another you know the 80-bit address
would be wrong the 48-bit address would
be fine
and so there was machinery built into
the architecture you know for recovering
from the situation where devices moved
between networks
and xerox didn't
do what they should have done
which was to make all the specs public
you know to encourage
implementation and deployment by you
know everybody on the planet
if i remember right they tried to hold
xns closer to their chest
as a proprietary protocol and that was a
horrendous mistake
and that is not perhaps the only factor
but certainly one of the factors
in xns not gaining traction so
while this isn't directly related to the
topic
of the fallacies of distributed
computing it does
touch on something that is related to
them
which is the whole issue of the benefit
to the developer of a standard
that comes from making that standard
open
because the developer of the standard
and the promulgator of the standard
even if they don't have full control
over it are first out of the gate
and they have probably a deeper
understanding of it than anybody else
great example of that is adobe you know
i mean i did ghost script right it's a
second implementation of
postscript but as one of my friends
adobe once said
that my business was about as much
concern
as a competitor adobe as a flying on
elephants
because you know adobe had this entire
team of developers
and deep understanding of all the issues
behind raster image processing and i
didn't you know i was a software guy who
started out not knowing much of anything
about graphics
so you know they're still the flagship
and the fact that they made those specs
open and in fact put a
good bit of resources into publishing
them and making them be really good
specs
created this tremendous market for
postscript and later for pdf
and a tremendous amount of that
expansion accrued to adobe if xerox had
understood that phenomenon with respect
to xns
who knows what the networking world
would have looked like today yeah and
that so far is a recurring theme in our
conversation which is
you know what could have been had things
been different and i think that's a
great transition absolutely
yeah and it's a great transition to the
details of the fallacies now because
you know the approach to these say 25
years ago
may be different than what it is now and
along the way
and also might have been different had
things gone differently
in relation to some of the conversations
or strategic
either lapses or what have you you know
as it relates to these
these companies and again with xerox you
know while i'll put links in the show
notes for
sun microsystems and xerox for those who
don't know who they are
although i think xerox is most infamous
for the
people who might be familiar with xerox
park and the fact that they basically
created the graphical user interface
which of course was commandeered
borrowed however you might say by others
[Applause]
yes well i was there when pretty much
all of that was happening but that's
a discussion for another day it is
well the fallacies this is interesting
too we don't go too deep into
the who's and the what's in the wise and
wherefores you kind of reviewed it a
little bit as we began
but you know the sort of the original
four and then four
that you added in your report and then
there's a ninth that people might see
from time to time around the internet
though it doesn't show up in the
wikipedia article
attributed to james gosling who we can
also put a link to james in the show
notes but
i'm going to review the fallacies real
quick and then what we'll do is
let's take each one at a time and let's
talk about why it was relevant
25 years ago and what's changed in
relation to that and either how it's
been addressed
or perhaps they've become less relevant
in the time frame since
you and your colleagues the son first
created this list so the fallacies are
the network is reliable
latency is zero bandwidth is infinite
the network is secure topology doesn't
change
there is one administrator transport
cost is zero
the network is homogeneous and finally
we all trust
each other so that first fallacy the
network is
reliable that even seems to have some
relevance
to what you were saying before about
xerox and the xns protocol
but let's talk about the genesis of this
idea at sun and how it was relevant back
then and how it's still relevant today
well so i don't actually know the
genesis of the first four
but what i can say about reliability is
if you look at
reliability in the context of network
systems
which of course i really understand best
from the software side
you have reliability enhancers
potentially at all levels of what's
called the protocol stack
so you know down at the bottom level you
may have
you know check sums on the packets that
cause the hardware or something very
close to the hardware to do re-transmits
then you know at the next level up you
have tcp windowing
and then it's at the level above that at
the application level
that unreliability tends not to be
addressed
now at the time 25 years ago
as i recall maybe not campus computing
but wide area computing
networking was not as reliable as it is
today
so at the time software correction for
outright
you know transmission errors
may have been relevant today i think
it's fair to
say that it is not that
we now have enough experience with error
detection and error correction
within you know the kind of the
ubiquitous levels of the protocol stack
that reliability in terms of data
corruption as seen at the software level
is just not a factor anymore however
what
is still tremendously relevant is
outages is interruptions in service
and that is still being handled badly
so error handling on network errors i
think
to the extent that even was relevant is
not particularly relevant now
handling timeouts handling failures to
transmit
is still very important and software
generally deals with that very badly
and i'll give an example that just came
up in the you know in the last week
so my husband uses an iphone and he does
a lot of
email on the iphone when he tries to
send email from the iphone
if the transmission fails number one
he says the iphone doesn't tell you
about it and number two
it doesn't try to re-transmit you have
to
notice that the message is still in the
out queue
and tell it to transmit again
so this is terrible terrible user
interface design
it's terrible architecture and it's a
result
of a mistaken or
i was going to say mistaken attitude but
i would say ignorance or lack of
foresight about reliability
yeah and it violates in a way the
principle of least surprise
which is that's not what any normal user
would expect an email system to do
well certainly not a normal user who's
used to desktop computing
but that's also another discussion sure
well as far as network reliability goes
you've mentioned
you know before the idea of not being
addressed at the application level and
it sounds like that's basically what
you're saying at the transport level the
hardware that as long as we're not
talking about you know full outages but
error correction and things of this
nature are in a way we could say solved
problems but then
to say therefore we don't need to
address it at the application level
is just another reflection of this
fallacy happening
pretty much every day still right i
agree with that the only
you know kind of distinction that i
wanted to make was that that
dealing with errors at the application
level i think is not really necessary
dealing with outages or interruptions at
the application level
is still extremely relevant yeah and as
kind of a little postscript of that i
should say that one of the things that
annoys me the most
is that when there is you know a failure
to transmit or you know some kind of
outage
i'll see generally speaking that
something is not happening
but being able to get any information at
all
about why or where the outage is
applications a generally don't share
that
and b the levels of the stack underneath
them
may not be set up to provide that
information so
that is an oversight on reliability
in the lower levels of the stack you
know if that is in fact the case
that makes sense and i see attempts to
try to resolve this a bit more
explicitly
with new protocols such as grpc which
you know flat out has a deadline within
the payloads that you send by default
and so there's an example of making
timeouts front and center it's like you
should expect this thing
to be either processed by a deadline and
if not
you should be ready to handle the fact
that it wasn't processed as opposed to
http which is
much more loose in that regard it is but
you know you mentioned timeouts so
something that i've been having an
ongoing wrangle with
my broadband provider about we're out in
the country and
we have a wireless broadband and
it is extremely annoyingly
unreliable and even when i call up their
tech support
sometimes i can't get any any
information from them about where they
think the problem is
and it's not clear that they even have
that information
so for example something that i believe
they don't have
is i don't believe they have good hop
by hop outage logs
if they did they'd be able to say oh
yeah
you know the problem is in our
connection to the backbone you know the
problem is in this intermediate link
between where you are at our hub
the problem is between our antenna and
your point of entry
the problem is beyond your point of
entry that's something they ought to be
able to tell me
they ought to have that information and
they don't
so it's not just a matter of problem
recovery
i think this particular fallacy
also leads to inadequate
tools for problem diagnosis and
communication
absolutely and of course you told me
that we're in the middle of recording a
podcast
from hundreds of miles of distance from
each other that your network is not
reliable so hopefully the fallacy will
not bite us as we're here recording this
well as it happens
i have an office that's not at my home
and it has
very very reliable dsl broadband and
that's where i am right now
oh well that's good to know so but back
home in the country
i imagine not only is the network as
reliable
one fallacy that you clearly live and
breathe on a daily basis but
that leads very well into the second
fallacy which is
people build applications and systems
assuming that latency is zero
right so this is something that's
actually come up
in my own interactive work when i'm here
at the office and interacting with a
server back at the house
one of the failure modes of the wireless
broadband
is not a complete loss of connectivity
but is
multiple retries that may cause things
as simple as
you know as character echoes to get
delayed by many seconds
and when that happens sometimes
one isn't sure whether something
actually happened or not
and you know you spoke about timeouts
timeouts aren't a bad idea
but for an application to be able to
tell you
whether something is in the process of
happening or not
would be i think really valuable to
users
and so they're really two aspects of
latency and one of them actually
relates directly to the next fallacy on
the list there can be latency caused
by you know the latency in the transport
of
any individual packet but there can also
be response latency
that's caused by application developers
having
unreasonable expectations or simply not
having thought
about the amount of data that has to be
transported
for given interaction so
you know because the broadband bandwidth
has been steadily increasing this is
less important than it has been in the
past
but even today the difference in
responsiveness
between graphics heavy
web pages and more i should say
information oriented web pages the
difference in responsiveness can be
quite noticeable to the user
you know if the user was on a
you know 100 megabit lan you know they
might not see any difference at all
but if you know if they're on the other
side of a broadband connection
who's you know whose bandwidth is only a
few hundred kilobits a second
then they are going to see that and i'm
in the process of developing
actually my first web application and
that actually is an issue
because the server for that application
is on the other side of that wireless
connection
and that wireless connection in one
direction is
typically only about 500 kilobits a
second
so if you have a web page that's you
know
20 kilobytes 20 kilobytes is
160 kilobits so just transmitting that
page
takes a third of a second and
while that is an artifact of bandwidth
and not
of latency at the network level it shows
up
as latency at the user level and so the
two are really connected
absolutely and when you consider that
most web applications are loading more
than one resource at a time
then that's going to lead to cascading
effects and you know you often
run into those situations where a team
says you know or people ask why is web
app slow and you just got to open up
your developer tools and you see
the chattiness of all of these
individual interactions and they just
can compound
indeed in fact a change that i actually
made in my application part way through
development
it used to store the
common javascript code the css
and the main page on three separate web
pages and the browser had to make three
separate requests for them
and simply sending all the data
in one request actually made a
noticeable improvement in the
responsiveness of the application
so that kind of thing yeah and you know
what's funny is we may not even have to
worry about that as much in the near
future
because http 2 and then a quick protocol
which
all referenced in the show notes you
know these protocols are coming out that
can actually allow
multiple requests to be fulfilled along
the same connection
whereas you know what we've had since
the beginning of the internet is more of
this
you know per resource requires its own
you know connection and there's not this
ability to sort of inline these requests
so
some of that is going to be hopefully
somewhat resolved but
sounds like you're not so sure well the
thing is that what you just described is
doable now
because http is a connectionless
protocol so
if the browser and the application of
the browser are multi-threaded
the browser can issue multiple http
requests
and have them basically you know be a
convoy
going through the network in one
direction and having the responses come
back in a convoy in the other direction
and i suspect that part of the reason
that doesn't happen is that
the rules for sequentiality versus
parallelism
in loading multiple components of a web
page
are perhaps not thought about as often
or as carefully as they could be
and of course if a page in turn has
references to another page that has to
be done sequentially
because you can't make the second
request until the first page until the
first
one has been satisfied so what you're
just describing
undoubtedly will make the situation
better and will make it easier to do
well
but i think at this point the issue is
not so much that
you couldn't queue http requests but
as that it is awkward to do within
the current technologies yeah and that's
a that's a good
thing to point out i think you know a
lot of it is how the browsers have
implemented things has an impact and
most browsers have some kind of a limit
on your connections which is
kind to the server because you know if a
browser could have a thousand
connections
you know you're gonna have ddos attacks
basically just by regular usage of your
of your system so there's sure there's
some throttling and things of that
nature that
that help so i noticed something is what
you're saying there is the inner
relationship between these fallacies as
well they can't really be taken
necessarily independently as you were
just demonstrating here that latency is
zero and bandwidth is infinite there's
some
interplay between how those fallacies
behave in the real world and there are
other connections on this list
so for example i mean we're not there
yet but the connection between number
four the network is secure
and number nine we all trust each other
their connections between those two
and their connections between number
five the topology doesn't change and
number six there is one administrator
those are also connected so you know
we'll get there in due course
elastic enables the world's leading
organizations to put their data to work
using the power of search
whether it's connecting people and teams
with content that matters
keeping applications and infrastructure
online or protecting entire digital
ecosystems
elastic's search platform is able to
surface relevant results with speed and
at scale
learn how you can get started with
elastic's search platform for free at
elastic.co
se radio
sure and that's a great opportunity to
transition to number four which is
the network is secure and as we're
diving into that
it again it occurs to me as well that
it's interesting how many of these
fallacies
they seem to pertain greatly to the
applications that use the network
not necessarily just to the network
itself and maybe that's something
that people haven't recognized before is
they're about networking but it sounds
like in some ways the fallacies are more
about
the expectations we have of the network
and how we use the network
because in some ways the network you
know the networks we have have
resolved a lot of these problems as you
pointed out before at the transport
layer
but at our apparel we ignore them at the
application level
absolutely and in fact for number four
which we're just about to talk about
the network is secure there's a saying
in the security community which you know
i'm not
the security guy but it's kind of stuck
with me which is
that in a layered system security can be
lost at any level
so the situation with network security
is actually
kind of interesting because the other
thing
to go along with what you just said
about the fact that these issues are not
just about the network infrastructure
but about the application is
as well there's a third thing that
they're about which is the environment
of use in the early 1990s
networking was very new and
an awful lot of the networking that was
happening
was happening within technology
organizations within research centers
probably within the military i wouldn't
know and
where for example you know people
started out
with an experience of latency being
essentially zero
because practically all of their
networking was on campus or
inter-organization networking
great point and now well it's kind of
interesting we went through
an era in which bandwidth was a big
problem
because consumers you know end users
non-technical users were piling into the
network world faster
than the telecoms or whoever could build
the capacity
and now the pendulum has to some extent
swung back the other way
you know it's now pretty routine you
know to do consumer level
real time or near real-time video
conferencing
so bandwidth isn't infinite but the
importance of that particular fallacy
you know went way up for a while and has
now gone
back down again somewhat whereas for
number four
the network being secure the importance
of that issue
has just continued to go up because
first of all
you know first we went from a situation
where almost all the networking was done
within
you know fairly well established trust
boundaries
to a situation where you know all of a
sudden we have these all these consumers
piling onto the network
and then we're now in a situation
where number one because of
malware the security of
the end users is much more difficult and
more complicated
than it was 20 years ago and i have a
whole wrap on malware which
is also for another day and also
with the use of networking including
broadband networking
within the government and within
higher security environments
the incentive for bad players
to attack networking has
increased greatly so the level of
sophistication
of security challenges and security
threats has also risen
dramatically compared with 30 years ago
which is a great point the more people
are on the network
then the more incentive there is for bad
actors to try to capitalize the more
people there on the network and
more specifically the greater the value
of the information being transmitted
and the greater the value of that
information
not being revealed the greater the
incentive
now you know on the flip side the
situation
has improved it hasn't i believe
improved commensurate
to the rise in threats but for example
you know the fact
that https and smtp
over tls the fact that at least hop to
hop
encryption is now becoming kind of the
the norm
that is certainly an improvement in a
big class of security situations
sure and that's hop to hop now where
would you see possibly there being
other areas where maybe it hasn't been
addressed well
so let me give you an example if you
look at email
end-to-end email security is a
known i wouldn't go so far as to say
it's a solved problem
but there are usable technologies for
end-to-end
email encryption and there are products
out there that do it
i think the signal does it i think
telegram does it i think there are a
couple of others
but in an example of something that
causes problems to
i think perhaps in all of these areas
google will not do it
because their business model depends on
their being able to read people's emails
[Music]
and similarly i think i have no data to
back this up
and i'm not generally a conspiracy
theorist but
i wouldn't be surprised if there had
been
some behind-the-scenes discouragements
let's say from the nsa which had the
effect
of end-to-end encryption not being
built in from the start in the email
applications offered by for example
microsoft and apple
yeah which is so interesting because and
again i and i agree with you it doesn't
really take conspiracy theories to
explain a lot of things it just takes
following the incentives
and of course there are people who'd
have an incentive to do what you just
described and yet ironically
it leaves those same entities prone to
attacks themselves so it's sort of it's
sort of a
doubly bad impact that is true although
you do have to distinguish a little bit
between the entities being vulnerable
and the entities
services or customers being vulnerable
no that's true too
right so i mean i'm sure that
well i'm not sure i wouldn't be
surprised for example if
google used more secure
email storage and transport within the
organization
than they support for their customers
but that's pure speculation
and again but it would be the incentives
would probably bear that out whether
it's true or not but it it seems like
it's plausible at least based on the
incentives
sure so at any rate so that's kind of
you know
the capsule summary which is that
security is now much more on people's
radar
hop to hop encryption is becoming used
widely a lot of the security issues now
are ones that are not in the network per
se
their issues of phishing and their
issues of malware penetration
of the end users absolutely and i also
think of other things such as
mtls which is mutual tls and zero trust
networking are becoming
you know more common but again even if
you're dealing with these things at the
network layer
that doesn't mean that the payloads that
are going over that network
are secure and that's a good point you
bring up there
is you know the network is secure isn't
just about the transmission
it's also about the payload within the
transmission and if we assume that
that's secure
because the network is secure assuming
the network actually is secure
we still have problems that are being
left unaddressed there such as
email not being secure i mean the
payload may be secure in the sense
that you can have a very very high level
of confidence that it hasn't been
corrupted in transit
the issue of what that payload does when
it arrives
that is exactly part of the larger issue
of
network use and that has people don't i
believe have
a good handle around yet yeah don't
spend enough time
thinking about it and designing systems
to deal with it
well we've gone through the four
original fallacies from sun
that you certainly included in your
report but now we're about to move into
the four
that you contributed in your time at sun
and this fifth one is near and dear to
my heart as a software architect because
i think a lot of times topology is left
undiscussed or not really
considered appropriately and a lot of
architectures are tightly and
in a similar way we described before
about xns decoupling the routing from
the network and
i think this is a pretty common problem
generally with the assumption that
the topology doesn't change and it's
also we based on that we make
assumptions about our application
architectures that couple us to topology
so one of the things that has definitely
changed tremendously in the last 30
years
is the fact that so much of network
usage is now
based on mobile devices so networking
has had to evolve to deal with a
situation
where the topology at least at the edge
is changing constantly
and you know new protocols have evolved
for that
but they are at least to my eye
as a non-networking guy to my eye they
seem
a little jerry-rigged so
if you want to do tcp networking and you
have a device
that's moving from one network to
another you have to have protocols you
know for to change its ip address as
it's moving
and once you have that you know once you
recognize that that's happening
then you have on top of that the
difficulty of maintaining sessions
you know if you're talking on a cell
phone on a long distance trip
long distance road trip or train trip
your cell phone is going to be handed
off from one tower to another as you
travel
and the protocols for
dealing with that constant change in
connectivity
have to take that into account and as i
said before you know ipv4
you know has required you know this
extra layer on top of it
that doesn't play with applications very
well if the application
well it may not play with applications
or operating systems
as well as a location independent
addressing scheme would
but so that's i mean that's really all
that i i would have to say about that
the genesis by the way of this was that
while i was at sun
i was hearing constant you know
mutterings and gripings
both from users and to a lesser extent
from network administrators
that oh you know so-and-so moved his
office from here to there and that put
him on a different network and yeah
yeah you know that problem just you know
doesn't have to exist if you have
the right addressing architecture down
at the bottom level
but we don't we don't so that problem is
going to be with us
in ipv6 you know to be perfectly honest
i don't remember what they did about
that
it'll expose my ignorance to say that i
don't remember whether ipv6 uses
location independent ids or not
or whether it still combines routing
with addressing
yeah i'll have to plead ignorance there
somewhat as well i know because of the
length of the address space
one of the intentions for my
understanding was to enable more
iot or internet of things type scenarios
although as you're describing the xns
protocol it sounds like once again xerox
was ahead of their time but the
execution was left to be done by someone
else
yeah so yeah that's right i mean my old
colleague butler lamson
who by the way originally gave me the
idea for just in time compilation and i
don't think has been adequately credited
for it
once said the single worst mistake that
you can make in the design of a system
is not to make an address space big
enough
well we might need to add that to the
list of the hardest things in computer
science which are
right it's what is it it's naming things
cash and validation
those are the two and then it's off by
one problems but now there's a fourth
which is
[Laughter]
failing to make a large enough address
space butler published a great paper
that talked about caching and cash
invalidation
also oh that's great that's great i will
look for that and try to put that in the
show notes
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you please visit
s e radio.net slash survey to share a
little information
about your professional interests and
listening habits it takes less than two
minutes to help us continue to make
essie radio even better
responses to the survey are completely
confidential that's
s-e-radio.net survey thanks for your
support of the show we look forward to
hearing from you soon
[Music]
the issue of changing topology is also
coupled with the next issue of
administration
you know even at sun which theoretically
should have had
a single administrator for all the
network connectivity issues in the
company
they sort of couldn't because you know
people moved offices and moved devices
and those things you know really should
be handled at the localized level
there shouldn't have to be an
administrator to deal with that
but that's only administration as it
relates to topology
now administration as it relates to
policy
you know which is on the wikipedia page
is a different issue
and i think that what is one of the
things that has become
pretty clear in these 30 years in
networking
and which i think generally has been
handled
is the realization that the potential
of networking and internet working can
only be realized
if there are well-established standards
that people actually implement and
of course every company every company
has business incentives
to add their own bells and whistles that
only work within the company
you know and that's you know that will
always happen but
what has made the internet as successful
as it has
as it has been is the fact that
it has done as good a job as it has
being standards based so the
relationship of that
with this fallacy here is
to say that the best
administration at least of some things
is
administration that doesn't need an
administrator
it is administration on the basis of
standards
yeah that's a great point i'm an
extremely strong believer
in good open standards and i think
i mean i'm also a great supporter of
open source software
but i believe that open standards for
both software
and data formats are more important
than the software itself being open
source
say that again i believe that good open
standards
both for software interfaces and for
data formats
are more important than for software
itself to be open source i think that's
a great insight
yeah absolutely and i think that's a
great point you mentioned interfaces and
formats and
maybe some clarification there but when
you mean interface you could basically
say in a sense it's the api i don't mean
a web api but it's it could be but it's
what's exposed how you interact with
this thing
and then the data that flows from it
into it right so
my interfaces for software really did
mean api and you know for networks of
course it's the protocols
but this also applies to the data
formats too many applications are data
jails you use them to create
you know data of great value to you
but you are then locked to that
application
to be able to share the data
convert the data extract from the data
you know do operations on that data
i won't go into this you know at
tremendous length but
my other careers is as a musician as a
composer
and the two leading commercial
musical score editing programs finale
and sebelius
both deliberately not only refuse
to publish the formats of their data
but at least sibelius actually goes to
some trouble to encrypt it
so they do not want any third party
to be able to read the data read the
information that you created
using their application and i think
this is well we're on the air so i'll
just say i think this is
very unfortunate it is unfortunate it
sounds like you know microsoft
office before they changed it to an open
standard and then that changed a lot of
things and it didn't seem to hurt
microsoft to
make this not that and i'm not
commenting on how good the standard is
i'm just saying it didn't hurt microsoft
but something that you should know is
that there's a difference between
making the form of the standard open
and making the semantics of the standard
open
because even with docx format even with
the xml based format
being able to render a microsoft word
document
accurately when i say accurately render
it the same way as microsoft software
requires knowing a tremendous amount
about quirks and peculiarities of
microsoft's implementation
and that's why i said before that's
what's important is not only that the
standard be open
but the players that the implementers
recognize that it's to their greatest
advantage
to implement it faithfully well this has
all gone a little a little far afield
but sure it has back to the point about
administration i think the the idea that
standards are actually
they are a form of administration just
like the consumer market is a form of
regulation in a sense and so if you can
get sort of inbuilt administration
without an administrator then you can
have significant benefits from doing so
you can and that leads into a whole
fascinating discussion of political
philosophy and
i'm i'm going to have to stop myself
from going there yes
different podcast different episode but
from that let's move on to number seven
and intriguingly to me as i look at
seven which is transport cost is zero in
some ways it relates to number three
which is bandwidth is infinite
exactly there's a relationship there
yeah so
i'm trying to remember what was going
through my mind when i added that one to
the list
you know i don't know that i can really
add a whole lot to that because
i don't honestly remember exactly what
the charging model
for networking was like 30 years ago and
one of the things that is quite striking
is that today
the transport cost at least as seen by
users is generally zero
for users it is but ironically the
relevance of this i think has greatly
grown
for software engineers because very
often
they will design a system and i've seen
this multiple times in my career
without taking into account the
transport costs
and then sometimes depending on the
nature of the data and
the usage metrics and things of this
nature that
suddenly you discover your transport
cost is not zero and it can bite you
well so let me push on that just a
little bit okay
if you look at a company that's offering
some kind of service through the web
let's say
their primary usage based
cost is going to be server capacity
and it's my impression that for
you know for high bandwidth network
connections
t1s or oc3s or whatever they're called
i was under the impression that those
are
flat rate so within a fairly broad range
the transport cost it's not zero but
it's usage insensitive
now you know as your traffic builds up
you know then they're going to be times
when you have to
you know go to higher tiers of bandwidth
so my impression is that it's not
exactly
transport costs that you're seeing
but bandwidth or capacity costs and
that's possible
yeah and that's fair you know if you're
crossing clouds for example
there's ways that you can try to reduce
that by setting up you know mutual vpns
and things of this nature but
i think it's and you know to your point
you mentioned server capacity which
you know compute storage would be the
primary elements of that
right i still think not considering the
transport cost
in relation to bandwidth and things is
something we still need to be careful of
and i mean i could obviously be wrong
about this but
even if it's not the biggest issue that
we face it seems to me in some ways it's
in some ways more of an issue now maybe
than it was 30 years ago
in other words it was prescient of you
to see this then
when the pricing models were different
than they are now
interesting well okay this may be a
blind spot on my part because i don't
really have
much of anything to add perhaps might as
well so let's move on to number eight
right which you know somewhat has to do
with topology
intriguingly you know five and eight i
think there's a bit of a relationship
there it has something to do with
topology
but i think it has a lot more to do with
the point that we were talking about
earlier
which you know is not really exactly a
fallacy on the list
which is the issue of standards because
the adherence of a multi-network or an
internetwork is
to standards the less of an issue
homogeneity at the hardware level or at
the implementation level becomes
because the standards allow you to
because the standards
make the network not only appear
homogenous
but in operation
be sufficiently homogeneous
right and even if there's multiple
standards as long as they're
adopted appropriately and consistently
it's still a form of homogeneity it's
just maybe more of a composed
homogeneity rather than
like a dictated top-down homogeneity
perhaps one of my former colleagues jim
morris
who was a great source of rye sayings
once said and i like this so much that i
call it morris's dictum
that the great thing about standards is
that there are so many of them to choose
from
yes yes and that is a problem of course
but the thing is that yes i mean
heterogeneity is an issue
and the thing is that i can't say i have
i have a lot of insight
into what this observation translates
into when you're developing
well in my case networking software the
thing is
you can only go so far because
one of the big issues in
heterogeneous environments is that the
very semantic
model of what it is that's being
represented may be different
i don't know enough about network
technology in detail to give you an
example
but i have a good one from an arena that
i'm more familiar with
which is musical score representations
so for example one musical score
representation may say
okay you know you have multiple staffs
and you have notes on each staff right
there's a different score representation
that may say okay
you have multiple staffs but you may
have more than one voice on each staff
and so now you know notes get linked
together because they're all part of the
same voice
and then that representation it may even
have the concept of a voice
going from one staff to another and
coming back again you see this sometimes
in
in piano music where you have what
amounts to a single voice and it has to
transition from one hand to the other
you can't do automatic conversion
between those two formats because one of
them has
information in it that the other one
just doesn't
and you know if i had time to think i
could probably come up with some
examples
of this in the networking world so from
what i can see
the best approach to heterogeneity in
the networking world
has simply been to get rid of it
by a you know a community-based process
that develops standards
that everyone is willing to sign up to i
think
there is more awareness of this as an
issue than there was 30 years ago
because 30 years ago networks and you
know networking hardware and software
weren't kind of you know
butting up against each other the way
they do today and i also think
that as i said before i think the
industry hasn't done
that bad a job of actually carrying it
out and i think that makes sense
i'll give you an example html5
there's some things about html5 i really
don't like but
it is a part of networking technology
in my opinion even though you know it
isn't part of of transport
where the industry has done a
creditable job of moving a standard
forward
to include new areas of application
and new opportunities i think of the
power grid and the mistake that someone
could make of assuming that the power
network is homogeneous and
failing to recognize that you know some
power grids are on 50 hertz some are on
60 hertz
and if you don't take that into account
you're going to have problems and that's
one of many examples of
if you assumed the power grid is
homogeneous you know across the world
you'd have issues and there are ways to
resolve it but
yeah but that's a great example and it
does kind of tie back to what i said a
moment ago
which is that if you kind of know what
the
space of heterogeneous alternatives is
then you know not keeping them in mind
is definitely a fallacy of development
it's
when you know when you have spheres of
influence or spheres of deployment
that come in contact with each other for
the first time and you have
entities that have may have started out
from quite different assumptions that
now have to be able to talk to each
other
that's where the problems really come up
that makes sense
there are tons of good science fiction
stories about this absolutely well and
even the power grid you know what i just
described is basically two
different standards right not right to
completely
you know wild west we're doing whatever
we want and now we're trying to
interface that would be the network it's
homogeneous
at its worst if you you know assuming
you believe that fallacy
but the power grid is a good example
there's 50 hertz versus 60 hertz
there's a 110 versus 220. so
yeah absolutely well and it used to be
you had to check with the voltmeter to
make sure that what you were getting out
of the wall was what you expected for a
particular device and we've resolved
we've resolved that problem and in a
similar way a lot of these things have
been resolved with the way that the
network
the global network works yes
so yeah i mean these issues are all
still there
and as we've seen you know going through
them some of them have been resolved
better than others and you know some of
them still aren't sufficiently on
people's radar
but you know with the additional 30
years of experience with
small scale and then large-scale
networking i'm temperamentally a
pessimist
no really i am but with respect to the
issues that we've
you know that we've just been over here
you know i have
you know pretty sort of cautiously
optimistic outlook
well you might have said that until we
get to number nine i don't know maybe
you can tell me but number nine
is not originally part of the eight
fallacies
but you have mentioned me previously
that it does belong on the list
and we're not sure of the genesis
possibly james gosling but let's talk
about
number nine and perhaps the source of it
and why you think it belongs on the list
well so it's really an expansion of
number four
and it extends beyond the boundaries of
the physical network
the issue of security and you know it's
stated in kind of an informal way
if i were going to restate it i would
say something like
the communicating parties trust each
other
or the party that you're communicating
with is trustworthy
yeah i think i think that would be the
way i would say it the party that you're
communicating with is trustworthy
okay and assuming that they are is the
root of this fallacy
is a fallacy because i mean
again this is a much much larger
philosophical question of
you know what's an appropriate level of
trust what are appropriate kinds of
trust what are appropriate trust
guarantee mechanisms
these are you know age old questions
of human relations and they're also
age-old questions
of business relationships of contract
of law you know they come up over and
over again
in the context of networking i alluded
earlier
to what i think are the two big
edge security problems that i don't
think we have a very good handle on yet
you know one of them is phishing and the
other
one is end user malware
and i believe that there are known
deployable proven technological
approaches that would tremendously
reduce
the risk of end user malware i don't
think those approaches
are being deployed because they would
have a very high commercial cost
and what we're seeing instead is bizarre
and byzantine attempts to mitigate them
for goodness sake at the cpu level
there's
junk that's been slathered into the more
recent intel cpu designs
specifically to try to do certain kinds
of
sandboxing and you know bad code
detection at the cpu level
and i think that this is you know
horrendously misguided
but i mean those are the two sources
that i
see of end-to-end trust issues
namely whether the other end is either
deliberately and knowingly inadvertently
and ignorantly being malicious
con 42 is a new series of must-watch
tech conferences
it's online and free to attend with
hybrid events coming next year
com com42 conferences cover topics like
cloud sre
chaos engineering machine learning and
quantum computing as well as programming
languages including python golang
rust and javascript register for free at
con42.com
sc radio that's c o n f
number four number two dot com slash
s e radio see you there for the ultimate
answers
at the end of the day from a networking
standpoint the solutions might be quite
similar but from a human standpoint
obviously intentionality
you know plays a big role in all of this
and i love the point you made about you
know so much of this has to do
it relates to so much more about things
like political philosophy and human
systems of communication
and connection and you know really at
the end of the day the network is
about us it's about people and how we
communicate and how we interconnect with
each other
it is and that's been so much more true
in the covet era when so much more human
interaction is
being network mediated absolutely and
you know hey the network certainly has
improved in 30 years because
i think for those of us who are very
technologically savvy and even those who
might be less so
covert would have been quite different
30 years ago than it was in
2020 and we can attribute a lot of that
to the technological expansion and
improvements that we've had over the
last decades
yeah that's a great point yeah i mean
you know to think about what it must
have been like
in the great pandemic 100 years ago that
was
in the late nineteen teens the telephone
was a fairly new technology radio wasn't
even widespread
yes even electricity was was not
universal universal point that's right
absolutely
well peter this has been a fascinating
conversation and i'm so
thankful that you've joined me on the
show if people want to find out more
about what you're up to where would you
recommend that they go
well so what i'm up to these days is i'm
basically not doing
software technology anymore i'm a
composer
so if you want to see what i'm up to go
to www.lp
okay lpb.org but you did
now true confession though you did tell
me you're writing your first
web application so there's some software
still going on
oh i do all kinds of software but you
know i think i might have said this to
you when we spoke earlier
you know how a lot of people mostly men
you know like to tinker with old cars
and old motorcycles
it's sort of like that with me and
software you know
it's in my it's in my blood i love doing
this stuff
i'm just not like doing it in public
this application that i'm building it's
not a commercial application
it's something to help our household
manage the
plethora of tasks and projects that we
seem to be engaged in
and you know it might be good enough to
be a great commercial project someday
but as might have said earlier
it's built on an architecture that
doesn't scale up
and that has other limitations and you
know some of them relate to these
fallacies i mean
it relies on it on a low latency network
and i know that
but the thing is i know that i knew that
going in and
i said okay you know you have to
understand what problem you're trying to
solve
the problem i'm trying to solve is local
to a household
it doesn't have to deal with some of
these issues
know your problem know your use case and
don't forget the fallacies of
distributed computing while you're at it
absolutely you don't need to boil the
ocean and build a cloud architecture
just to manage your housing
that's true so thank you very much for
having invited me this has been a lot of
fun for me too as well
yeah thanks so much for being here this
is jeff doolittle for software
engineering radio
thanks for listening thanks for
listening to sc radio an educational
program brought to you by ieee software
magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se-radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening